welcome to meditating with Chandra Vicki
I'm a cognitive psychologist in the
cognitive scientists at the unit of
University of Toronto where I teach
academically and study scientifically
mindfulness and related topics like
Insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness the cultivation of
wisdom and the aspiration to
enlightenment I've also been practicing
the pasta meditation not a contemplation
Tai Chi Chuan and Chacon for over 29
years and teaching and professionally
for close to 20 years welcome this is a
progressive course the introductory
aspect of this course is actually
complete we've now moved into advanced
advanced techniques you're welcome to
stay but if this is your first time I
recommend you go to the links in the
notes for this video where you'll find
all the previous lessons to the
introductory course and then you can
catch up we will be doing a Dharma day
today which I teach a new practice or
principle every alternative Monday the
rest of the time we meet Tuesday through
Friday we sit every day Monday through
Friday
there's Q&A at the end please keep your
questions limited to the practices I'm
teaching within the course for more
broad reaching questions please come to
my daily a lot you YouTube livestream
qunit sorry not my daily my monthly
youtube live streamed Q&A it's every
third Friday of the month 3 p.m. Eastern
Time
please like this video scream to
increase the visibility in the YouTube
algorithm you're helping me to help as
many people as I possibly can on deeply
appreciative of that so as I said today
we are going to do a Dharma day but
we're going to do something a little bit
different because of what I'm going to
be teaching you with this Lexi o Divina
it's appropriate that we sit first we're
gonna have a shorter sit so I have a
little bit more time to go over the
practice with you so let's get ready
please let's set your
phones on do not start getting your
ready for your posture we're going to do
a shorter sit today so we have more time
for the Lexia so we're going to do a
10-minute sit right now please
so we will begin when I say together
begin
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
all right let's begin so Alexia Davina
is a practice it's a spiritual practice
that you should incorporate into your
ecology practices to complement the
meditation and contemplation and later
will of course have the flow exercises
as I bring in some moving practices
right this is the way in which you
should approach Donnell so I'm just
going to hold up some books first here's
a book my the first book for the first
books are from the Christian tradition
it's hard to get books outside of it
I'll show you this one here this is this
book on lectio divina renewing the
ancient practice of praying the
scriptures it's by basil Pennington it's
good this one is particularly good
sacred reading okay so it's the ancient
art of Luxio Divina by Michael Kate
Casey also really really really good
here's the original classic for this by
cuido a ladder of monks and twelve
meditations I don't recommend reading
this first I don't recommend reading
this first I recommend reading the other
two books and then reading this book
because this will be a little bit
obscure removed if you want
they've look that talks about Lexi Oh
from a non-christian tradition from the
Neoplatonic tradition there's a lot of
discussion in here in this book by my
Kupperman this is the book called living
theour Jia Jia Jia is a practice with a
set of practices within the OU Platonism
in connection with that for those of you
who are interested for when we are going
to do the wisdom Sangha I will a book
that will incorporate all of these
things together so that we can recover
the wisdom tradition of the West as I
continue to teach you the wisdom
traditions from the East Buddhism Taoism
we're going to take a look at this
important book okay this very important
book written by another cognitive
scientist Bruce McLennan this is called
the wisdom of cepacia and this is
discovering the spirit
secrets of ancient philosophy in
connection with that if you can these
are for down the road but I thought I'd
mentioned it now get two books by Arthur
versus Lewis who I highly recommend one
is the perennial philosophy Arthur Lewis
and the other is platonic mysticism by
Arthur versus Lewis so Alexia Davina as
you're no doubt seeing comes out of the
Neoplatonic tradition it gets taken up
of course within the Neoplatonic strand
of Christianity on
neoplatonism is our third verse Lewis
argues is basically the the spiritual
grammar of the Western wisdom wisdom
traditions one more book now for
specifically that you need to get in
conjunction with Alexio Davina because
this is the virtue that we are
cultivating in lecture Davina this is
the excellent book by Paul Woodruff
reverence
it's called reverence renewing of
forgotten virtue reverence renewing of
forgotten virtue okay so that's some
background alright so I recommend that
you get a poetry book and a prose book
I'm going to first now I always make
sure you've done meditation and or
contemplation of Praja before you do the
Lexia you have to get into the proper
state of receptivity so remember we
these texts whenever you wish of course
outside but now we're not reading for
information we're reading for
transformation okay so I'm gonna take
you through the four stages I'm teaching
you sort of a secularized version of
Alexio Divina that will resonate with
both the Neoplatonic traditions and with
the Christian traditions and if you want
to take this up as a specifically
Christian practice because you're
Christian or you want to renew
Christianity I hope this you'll find
this helpful
I'm nevertheless so there's four stages
what we're going to go through so first
of all I'll say what each stage is and
then we'll go through them and I'm gonna
review this a lot this week okay now
when I'm doing it I'm going to be doing
it as if I'm doing it for myself so you
have to understand that I'm I'm not
doing it with you in the sense that I'm
expecting you to have the same reactions
that
I'm modeling it to you so that soon as
we're done today as soon as we're done
today do another quick set maybe five
minutes and then with the two texts that
you have chosen take the practice up for
yourself okay all right so what are the
four stages so the first one is in
active engagement so what what that
means there's an active engagement
you're going to read the text and you're
going to read the text with an attitude
of reverence and you're going to read
the text with with the intention of
resonating with the text you may
actually say to yourself may I resonate
with this text and what you're what
you're doing is you're reading for
transformation you're going to read
aloud you're going to read as if almost
at this somebody else was reading it to
you and you were trying to open it up
from it that there is something in here
to be disclosed to you that you haven't
seen before
you're reading for transformation so
you're really engaging it what does that
mean when you read you look for what is
salient to you don't don't try and
explain why don't don't theorize
something will jump out at you something
will be catchy for you even if it
moderately sometimes will be strong
sometimes it will be moderate right so
try to know what catches you what's
salient to you okay so you're reading in
this reverential and then you're doing
this in active engagement and then you
do embodied emotion so pick up the
phrase that caught you my third salient
start repeating it to yourself almost
like a mantra and let up most of all
associations come up and as the same
time as you're doing that try to find
whatever imagery was in the what you
read and especially perhaps in what
standing up for you and do practice it
imaginably not imagining it in your head
imagining is if you are literally acting
out the metaphor so literal eyes that at
first act it out and let your emotions
associates right so I'll show you how to
do this but what you're doing is your
imagination you're acting it out and
you're mostly associating with it you're
really reaching into how much of your
ability to make sense of things it comes
up from your body
and how you're interacting with the
world and we've talked about this a lot
in the course okay so you've done
enacted engagement you've done embodied
emotion okay next you can do the
existential ethical move so what's the
existential ethical move the third-stage
the existential ethical is when you get
a sense of what it's like what you're
what what's it what's your perspective
like what's how is your world being
shaped right what would it be like to
live in this perspective that you've
engendered in the first two stages as if
you it became sort of your default mode
of consciousness what would it be like
to live this way how would you move
around the world really try to get a
sense of what it would be like as if
this became a second nature perspective
for you not just one that you were
realized
so really let it soak in this is this is
the existential ethical you're really
trying to see what would this feel like
as a way of life a way of being a way of
seeing the world and then that moves you
very mmediately to the fourth stage
which is the exstatic which literally
means to stand beyond yourself that's
what ecstasy originally means ecstatic
eternal from that perspective try to get
an inkling maybe even an insight what is
being disclosed to you about being what
is being disclosed you about the world
and correspondingly what is being
demanded from you so that you can
conform to that realization notice the
word I'm using to that realization what
is to be how do you would you need to be
transformed in order to conform to that
deeper reality that is being disclosed
to you okay so let's review and then
we're going I'm going to do it I'll talk
you through what it's like for me again
don't don't you're not supposed to be
having my experience I'm modeling what
it's like for me so that you can then do
it immediately when we're done today's
session for yourself okay so enacted
engagement set the intention to resonate
with the text to be transformed in the
reading read aloud but something catchy
let something grab you
embodied emotion emotionally resonate
with us but emotions and associations
come up with that also whatever
metaphors are in them literalized them
actually as if you were to you know
enact them alright really pick that up
you're really enacting and embodying the
emotion then the existential ethical
what would it be like if this way of
seeing became a comprehensive way of
being for you but this was your
comprehensive perspectival knowing your
default mode of consciousness how would
that be like how to imagine them it's
some sensitive and then when you're
within that the exstatic eternal what's
being disclosed to you maybe it's only
an inkling it might be vague feeling
there might be an inkling there might be
a full-blown insight anywhere on the
continuum is good ok what's being
disclosed to you about the world about
being and correspondingly what's being
demanded from you what what's calling to
you what transformation in order to come
into a greater conformity with that
deeper reality are you seeing is coming
to you is calling you ok so let's do it
now what you're gonna do is you're gonna
have two texts and what you do is you do
the four stages with your poetry because
poetry is easier because it has an
imagery in it it starts and then you'll
move to something more challenging your
prose right and so and then you do the
four and then you'll notice that your
mind naturally and spontaneously makes
associations and connections insights
between the poetry and prose let them
talk to each other as a way of talking
to you let them talk to each other as a
way of talking to you let them talk to
each other as a way of talking to you
okay so let's go through this so what I
know how I would do this is I set myself
and what I do is I have these two
objects you've seen them before this
this is a rock this is important to me
this represents to me the whole Zen
tradition Buddhism and Taoism this is
the fraud there's a neo platonic
tradition I carry them around in my
pockets and I do that so that throughout
the day they remind me they remind me of
my aspiration they remind me of my
commitment
and then I enact them here so I place
them in front of me you know may I
resonate with this text I put myself
into that state of reverence and that
state of reading for transformation not
just reading for information
now I typically don't leave very much
some people read a lot I find that when
you read too much it starts to get too
many things are getting called up at
once so this is this is what I was
reading today for that this is Gerard
Manley Hopkins okay as King Fisher's
catch fire
dragonflies draw flame has tumbled over
rim in round Ewell's
stones ring like each tucked string
tells each hung bells bow Swan fine
stump to fling out broad its name each
mortal thing does one thing in the same
deals out that being indoors each one
dwells selves goes itself myself it
speaks and spells crying what I do is me
for that I came so what called out for
me here is that you know finds tongue to
fling out broad its name so finds tongue
to fling out broad its name and so now
that's that's really catching for me
like finds tongue to fling a broad its
name and then I start to get emotional
associations I had a experience a
profoundly lucid altered state of
consciousness in which as I moved about
the world it was like everything was
singing its name I am a tree I'm a
flower on a blade of grass and so this
is coming to my mind right now how
everything is singing its name and now I
actually imaginal as if I was moving
around this room and that emotion is in
me again in that memory everything is
singing out its name everything is
singing and so I'm coming into the BN
mode with everything everything is
singing its name and calling to me and
then I move into what would it be like
if that was my constant perspectival
knowing my way of being and seeing in
the world if I moved around the world
and living my life everything seeing its
name put aside practical thoughts well I
can't live that way just what would it
be like what would it be like there have
Ison related to everything singing its
name like Hopkins was talking there
everything is singing its name without
being like what's just being disclosed
to me beginning an inkling of how I
would move into the being mode of how
everything would just be so present and
that that different kind of meaning that
that would be and what's that calling
from me that's calling from me I need to
remember this I'm so forgetful I treat
things at such a superficial way and
everything even the inanimate things are
singing their name would you like to
live this in a sense of this
what was it demanding for me what's it
calling from me and when I pick up the
prose text I think it's appropriate for
this one this is from Plato and this is
Socrates somebody I aspired to and what
he's doing here is exemplifying the
state of reverence that we're talking
about is a dialogue between Phaedrus and
Socrates this is why Phaedrus is the one
of the characters in zen and the market
zen and the art of motorcycle
maintenance by the way Phaedrus is at
the end of the dialogue but let us go
now that it has become less oppressively
hot Socrates
shouldn't we first offer a prayer
Phaedrus of course Socrates dear pan and
all you other gods who live here grant
that I may become beautiful within and
that whatever outward things I may be in
harmony with the spirit inside me sir
and whatever outward things I have may
be in harmony with the spirit inside may
I understand that it is only the wise
who are rich and I have only as much
money as
put person needs is there anything else
that we can ask for Phaedrus for me that
prayer is enough Phaedrus make it a
prayer for me too
since friends have all things in common
Socrates let's be going so what the
whole passage sings to me but what comes
out of this is may I become beautiful
within so may I become beautiful within
does that mean do I associate with that
how can I let go of older conceptions of
just physical beauty may be beautiful
within what does that mean there's
difficulty and challenge with this
reading but there's also a longing here
may happy beautiful within there's
something there there's something in
what Socrates is talking about starting
to touch it a little bit even a little
bit even an inkling azimuth may I be
beautiful with them what would it be
like what would it be like to see and be
this way a second nature always in touch
with that being beautiful within me I
become more beautiful with it I just
that softens me it makes me more
sensitive it's opening me up but it's
not it's not you know the it's not quite
beauty that we see in our culture it's
not that they're self aggrandizing it's
a humbling it's connected with a kind of
humility that you see in Socrates the
temperance that he needs the beauty
within walking around the world living
this way
what's disclosed about the world there's
a deeper sense of the beauty of things
and not picking up again on how things
are singing their name and that beauty
and inner beauty but I can only resonate
with from my inner beauty there's a
humbling the reverence starting to come
into a sense of what it would be like to
remember the sati to live this way
two texts are talking to each other the
beauty and everything singing its name
so that's the practice and get it a
little bit quick here because we have
limited time but what we have here is
right the inactive engagement
recited set your intention for
transformation and reverence recited
what catches then recited again as you
do emotional associations and you try
the imaginal enactment and then write
the existential ethical so enacted
engagement embodied emotion than the
existential ethical what would it be
like to live this way to see my way of
seeing and being was this way and then
the ecstatic eternal what's disclosed to
me what's demanded from me and let the
two texts talk to do that for each tax
but in the second reading let the two
texts talk to each other so that they
can talk to you then you can commit
yourself to trying to remember this
throughout the day you can set the
attention they remember and realize this
again and again throughout this day at
some point you may want to add to this
by picking up a Dharma practice by an
extra Dhamma practice which is study so
pick up a text that is written for
spiritual transformation that also has
commentary in it so you're not or at
least is extended commentary right now
I'm I don't recommend you doing this I'm
just giving you an example this is once
I wasn't work like Latinas there's a
translation and then there's commentary
at the back you can get books where you
can read through the Gospels and there's
commentary on it for those of you who
are interested in picking up under the
cosmic tradition there's this wonderful
trilogy the experience of insight by
goldstein freedom in disorder seeking
the heart of wisdom by Goldstein and
Court
remember cornfield in the puppy dog and
Insight Meditation the practice of
freedom and this is by goldstein not
trilogy is a very good trilogy you might
want to pick up you read these you don't
do lectio Divina on these you read these
but this is not just reading you study
you read it and you get the commentary
and you reflect so this is reading and
reflection okay my let my students and
my wonderful Sangha
that's practice and what I'll do is I
think it would be good right now if we
we move towards just a couple of quick
questions on Lexi oh and then what you
need to do that's why it how'd you get
the books they're ready here sit again
sit again don't worry you won't lose the
instructions I'm going to repeat them
one more time okay but sit again maybe
just for five minutes then take your
text do Lexi Oh on each one and also how
they talk to each other this is called
synthamax and therefore how they can
talk to you
so enacted engagement setting your
intention for reverence and
transformation what catches you taking
it up into embodied emotion repeated
again emotional associations memories
that come up what's stirring in you
enact the metaphor enacted enacted
emotionally not inside your head but is
if in the world existential ethical what
would it be like to live this way this
was your way of seeing and being and
then ecstatic external ecstatic eternal
what's being disclosed for you what neat
you may have a feeling an inkling or
full-blown insight what's being
disclosed to you about the world and
correspondingly what's being demanded
from you what transformation to bring
you into greater conformity with that
disclosure so a couple of questions
what is the poem book called again the
enlightened heart an ontology of sacred
poetry edited by Steven Mitchell the
prose book is the enlightened mind an
anthology of sacred prose edited by
Steven Mitchell should we intentionally
try to select contemporary poetry prose
or let the associations emerge as a
function of the practice
pick something that intuitively calls to
you yeah try to pick up something that
you two ative Lee calls to you and you
can have to play with things for a bit
but don't be too much of a dilettante
yeah it's not you have to commit to you
know once you've chosen a Tex commit to
it for an extended period of time
because this is going this is gonna a
band for you it's kind of ebb and flow
for you okay everyone so please as soon
as we're done today do is to go back
into you right at least find the core
for do some basic the past and perhaps
maybe some basic meta or maybe a little
bit of prana come on every much time you
have and then immediately you've got to
do this immediately do the Lexi Oh
Davina okay thank you for joining
everyone thank you so much for joining I
hope like she said I'm going to review
this again extensively and I'll do it
again
I'll review it on Tuesday on Thursday
and I'll do it again with you on
Wednesday and Friday I want you to thank
my wonderful friend and techno major
maher for all of his help my beloved son
Jason please subscribe to this channel
to be notified of the next video and on
the channel you'll find a lecture series
awakening for the meeting crisis a
discussion series voices with Rob a key
that helped develop all of these things
that were talking about more deeply and
more comprehensively please invite
others who might benefit by sharing this
series so it can help as many people as
possible I'll join the discord server
Brett pleasure of doubt is here you
there go there there's a great community
they're talking about all of this stuff
the link is in the description to this
video remember that we will be doing
this every morning at 9:30 Eastern Time
continuity practice more important than
quantity there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body
there's no friend no ally greater than
your own mind and body thank you for
your time and attention everyone I'll
see you all tomorrow
take care